all right welcome back cohort 6 Andrew
however you want to begin this
discussion on chapter two go for it sure
um probably yeah pulling up the textbook
might be a good
move
um I know that this is week two of
chapter two so I don't want to uh
reintroduce the entire chapters if you
haven't already spent a week on it but I
thought it'd be nice for anyone who
wasn't able to attend last week to just
kind of quickly skim what's going on um
so yeah this is chapter 2 the low road
to active inference in chapter one we
were introduced to the idea that there's
a high and low road to inference so um
the low road is more about the um sort
of the the the what or the the how of of
active inference and um as opposed to
the high road will where there will be
more disc discussion on the why and the
why of like why is this happening why
are agents doing this how do they
survive that's kind of the questions
getting at here this is getting much
more into sort of something like the
mechanics of the process um and it picks
up uh with the helm Holan perspective
which is a 19th century late 19th
century tradition uh that just began on
viewing uh perception as unconscious
Ence uh this idea is picked up more in
ideas such as the Basi and brain
hypothesis later on in the 20th century
and from just an act uh active inference
perspective we're treating not just
perception but also action planning and
learning all as basian inference
problems as well as deriving a
variational
approximation um for these problems to
overcome intractability problems um
with the helm holian tradition the kind
of Distinction about this versus other
historical cognitive science Traditions
is that rather than viewing perception
is only a bottomup process of sensory
States being fed into uh being turned
into internal representations of the
outside or some such thing like that
instead perception is viewed as an
inferential process that combines topown
prior information about the most likely
causes of Sensations with bottom up
sensory stimuli so we actually have this
as opposed to um perception being more
of an outside in process it's more of a
it's it's both right it's
bidirectional um we're introduced to
baz's rule which is just um incredibly
crucial to active inference as well as
just many other kinds of probability
problems I strongly recommend those who
are wanting to get into the maths to
kind of work on um just kind of
understanding baz's rule almost as like
a sort of Cornerstone from which to
begin um it can be viewed as a
posterior uh equaling and uh a fraction
that is uh the numerator is a prior and
a likelihood and then your denominator
is evidence and so what can happen is
that you can update any of these Quant
quantities in order to solve for another
quantity right so this this this can be
updated over time by taking in new
information that then update
everything else you can update your
priors your your posteriors which are
your beliefs at the end like at the end
of the process um and so what's nice is
that we can actually map all these
quantities uh onto the modeling process
and active inference it's so a
generative model in our case like an
agent um it could be a human being it
could be uh some other biological
organism or otherwise the generative
model is just a combination of PR uh
Pride PRI and um likelihood mappings so
priors would be something like
probability of X in the textbook um in
often times uh notation can also be like
uh probability of O which stands for or
excuse me S which stands for latent
States or hidden States um likelihoods
are probability of Y given X so y
condition on X or in other literature
can be viewed as um observ ations o
conditioned on S hidden Laten States so
we have these other
quantities um involved and yeah all of
those are updated using bases rule
um we have some additional um
information in that section box 2.1 goes
over gives a brief refresher on
probabilistic reasoning some Rule and
product rules for anyone who wants a
little bit of a who's completely you
know coming into this or or maybe took a
probability course some but maybe you
know it's uh the the knowledge is no
longer no longer there and need a bit of
a refresher um we have a nice example of
of an agent who confronts um you know a
frog or an apple and those are kind of
two example like hidden States in that
particular problem right so the agent
has its own beliefs about the
probability it will see a frog that it
will see an apple uh it's given a new
observation in the moment whatever the
thing is it's looking at it jumps and so
that's an
observation versus the S the X the
hidden states which are a frog or an
apple and so those get ma those get
linked together through um the the
likelihood in baz's rule as we uh as we
mapped a moment ago and so the agent
basically updates its beliefs about what
it's seen based on the observation it
just took in not sure what the thing is
it could be a frog could be an apple
took in a new observation it jumped uh
it has its own likelihood mappings oh if
it jumped then uh excuse me um yeah then
it will it'll draw inference from there
so we're also introduced other Concepts
like surprise basine surprise K
Divergence um importance of biological
plausibility um many of these theories
are being being drawn from Neuroscience
um and so there's there's emphasis on
things like cognitive costs of
computation um there's only so much
one's brain can do and so whenever you
consider how many computations would be
involved in you know any example beyond
what we just looked at like two hidden
States apples frogs um you can imagine
and practice immensely more than that uh
are being computed um presumably at any
any given moment so um so that's where
we end up looking at quantities like
variational free energy uh as well as
expected free energy by the end of the
chapter um and this chapter I would say
um this one's a really good Cornerstone
for just like really getting familiar
with a lot of what's going on in active
inference it's it's a pretty lengthy
chapter compared to the rest and um so
spending some time with the different
terms that are all kind of quickly being
introduced here is a good idea so I
guess I'll I'll kind of leave it off
there and ask is anyone um you know
curious about anything or more specific
questions about what are going on um in
in this chapter um it is a lot to say
again yeah
oh um so did the low road and high road
come to get came did it come about like
simultaneously or is it
like is it just
like U worked on like um like separately
and then they both just came in at the
same
time um I do
think uh Daniel would have uh a lot more
knowledge on this but as far as I'm
aware there's they're yeah these are
coming from various traditions and are
kind of a synthesis of
different um yeah different Traditions
or otherwise over time and then a lot of
it is kind of uh composed primarily by
Carl friston one of the co-authors of of
the
textbook yeah that's good answer a few
other thoughts the rhetorical device or
the metaphor was introduced by friston
in this like beyond the desert landscape
paper it's reference somewh theota
um any model that exists is going to
have a low road so to speak CU there's
always a how otherwise it's not being
it's just a a framework being discussed
and then any kind of aaic starting point
is its own kind of high road so low and
high road can apply different to to to
to probably to Frameworks other than
active
inference y um like kind of by analogy
like to almost to denit cranes and
skyhooks and like that kind of bottom up
and top down Theory and empiricism so I
think it kind of describes that
generally and then the special thing
about the low
road uh constructions and that lead to
active inference or like that are
represented by the active inference
gener model is exactly what Andrew said
which is that the Bas rule is embodied
totally by the generative
model and that describes this like broad
class of of
constructible but then compatible with
in this case free energy principle and
not necessarily something
else yeah I I guess my my thinking was
you know did it came from two minds or
was it from like one mind um using two
different um perspectives to uh to think
about you know um a solution to the
problem I think it was many more than
two overall like many people have raised
many different good points about how
something like has to be to persist for
example
and then obviously many people have
proposed different architectures and
there's multiple ways to do active so
it's kind of I think the you know maybe
get towards higher resolution maps for
the low on the high road and other
things like that yep okay I thank you
yeah David then Susan yeah so similar
along those lines if you go back to uh
the image 2.1 I think it was
um between the percentage uh frogs and
apples I think it was a comparison
so in terms of that likelihood at what
point are we talking about the same
thing in terms of like if you have a
belief structure of you know what
percentage of apples believe they're
frogs couldn't you wouldn't it be
commutative in the same way where frogs
would also have that same belief
structure of apples if that makes sense
in terms of you know occupying the same
space so self- inferential are you a
frog or are you an apple your prior
still need to updated in terms of that
correct but there would still be that
percentage would that percentage not go
away despite you know replacing those
priors in that
sense yeah that's very interesting
question so in this case this likelihood
model is the a matrix in figure 4.3
because it's describing the mapping
between is an apple or and what is the
observation so this is kind of an
exteroceptive a Matrix however the
metacognitive models treat like
ascending observations as observations
of metacognitive observers so in that
case that could refer to like
interceptive data coming in observ
interceptive observations or
introspective observations mapping to
unobserved States about what kind of
thing is generating those observations
like am I hungry given the stomach
sensation so it could be applied
internally as well to maybe some of the
things you're talking about yeah I guess
I was speaking more also in terms of uh
what how just said in terms of uh you
know of one mind or of you know more
than two minds as you had
mentioned okay thanks
Susan yeah so as far as um describing
the low road and the high road would it
be incorrect to um use a colloquial term
like Tactical for low
road tactical moves does anyone think
yeah go for
it yeah it's an interesting question um
I mean you know on the one hand I'm not
so I'm not so sure if if that can you
know be answered expressly maybe that's
the kind of thing that I think someone
might have to kind of do their own write
up on on justifying that as kind of
maybe like part of the active inference
ontology is to view it as
tactical um I mean if you were thinking
to just the context just within the
confines of this
chapter um and you're thinking about an
agent being
tactical um I would say this stuff
relating actually to maybe planning that
we see in later
sections um that might be more directly
linked just conceptually with the word
tactical in the sense of an agent is
comparing potential sequences of actions
or policies that it could take um it it
is scoring those based on the expected
free energy for each policy uh you end
up going with the one that has the
lowest expected free energy right so
that's a kind of like what should I do
here a series of paths I could take
here's the one that is least surprising
or at least is expected to have the
least amount of free energy returned
take that path right so it's almost like
strategizing now that that itself is
still kind of a loose analogy and that
you know yeah yeah I can see that yeah
so let me ask you another question that
may relate it relate it one one thought
Susan on that um Andrew that's that's a
good answer like doing the evaluation
and the the search is H is the how and
then there's other attributes of
planning that would make up like kind of
the high road of planning and I think
the stream to look at is
42 um so this is also very useful for
nested modeling and understanding the
composability of the nested modeling so
here it was like analogy to strategy
tactics control the center as being a
higher order simpler less tactical less
operational side and then their model of
a robot in a warehouse has this finer
scale that is like tactical that
describe the posture of the robot and
then a higher corser scale that was like
the location of it now this model itself
could be interpreted from a low road
perspective because even though this
higher order is about the location of
the robot it is still
constructed so there's probably aot to
look at it or to think about it
especially if you worked it outf
actually I think I think you got
strategic and tactical on both ends of
action and perception I mean that's what
kind of came to mind when he was he was
talking and and and so and I don't know
if this relates directly or not but when
we talk about Li high road and low road
policies that do they do they have
distinctly different
policies no they're meeting an active
inference because you only build the
active inference gener
model that's actually doing the
inference so they just come together in
that constructed
model yeah I think if it's useful
um I've almost wanted to bring this up
from an earlier question but um figure
1.2 in the chap in the textbook which is
actually in chapter one page seven um
this is just to illustrate like with
active inference in the center right
like these are the high and low roads to
active inference like it's not so much
that they're entirely distinct you know
things it's more about conceptually
these are two paths that you could kind
of take to kind of move towards standing
active inference right so it's like the
low road is kind of we're starting from
base theorem we're starting from
statistics numbers calculation
valuations so on and that's what this
chapter is about meanwhile the high road
is more about the free energy principle
so now we're more expressly talking
about things like like with perception
everything we've talked about so far and
scene chapter 2 we don't really see so
much actually about like an agent trying
to survive right we don't we don't quite
see that this is just like math right
like it's just doing stuff um not so
much like trying to it's only near the
end that we get mentions of like it has
preferences that go into planning and
things like that but really this is just
kind of the mechanical aspect it's yeah
the high Rogue will be more it'll give
us much more context and I also think it
makes active inference so much more
interesting when trying to think about
how how to apply it to different
situations
so
yeah
H so I guess one of the purposes of
active influence is so that we don't
have to
manually choose the pliers right
choose prior or choose
what because in I guess in real life
with organisms you know there's uh many
fires hidden fires that you know we we
don't know that lead to you know the
perceptions and decisions that you know
they they have um you know and it'll be
too much for us
to to try and emulate or
simulate
um
I
mean do we still have to generate the pr
beforehand for an
agent so that is something about active
inference that you know there's there's
been many conversations about this and
you know it can it could totally Branch
out into much bigger philosophical
questions but active inference doesn't
necessarily um have any guarantee of
what a a prior should be it doesn't you
know it's not very good whenever it
comes to origin stories um I I suppose
is one way of stating it it's more about
this is how things happen this is why
things happen I will say um if you're
coming from more of like a computational
modeling or coding perspective uh and
you'll see this much later in the
textbook in like chapter 7 for example
um but oftentimes what's done is you'll
establish some kind of vector of priors
over initial States um so you do kind of
have to hardcode those
um the thing is you can you can have the
agent you know interact with its
environment running trials and then it
can in fact from trial to trial update
its own priors right so so it's kind of
like once you get the the motion moving
it it kind of moves on its own so to
speak furthermore a lot of examples
whenever it comes to modeling many
people just start with uniform priors
like there's no there's not something
there necessarily that says you have to
have you know some very um you know
domain knowledge specific priors or or
something like unleash the agent with
uniform priors it doesn't know what's
going on presumably it will you know as
the low road mechanics play out it will
it will readjust its own priors it kind
of depends on the use case is the
simplest answer yep so so some um
so it can um generate it on price you
know if it's given um you know like
observations of like RGB you know an RGB
camera and
maybe yeah I don't know I guess it's
just some sort of you know sensory
input sure yeah it it it is not widely
or simply available that just because
like you made a active influence agent
is going to do arbitrary like infinite
generalization structure learning Etc
like those are very exciting directions
to consider the kind of beginning State
and the procedures for agents that could
do things like modify the number of
observations they received or understand
different policy
spaces so yep that's definitely to be
explored and then play around with with
the different components of that
separately and then bring them together
and see H how things go but if you just
look at like the PDP tutorial that is
not not going to do like open-ended
structure learning whereas maybe a
certain kind of rapper around the recent
structure learning paper would have that
kind of capacity but then not
necessarily like affect or attention or
something else that's explored in
different paper so it's always very
situational which capacities are
actually brought in Because unless
there's like some kind of open-ended or
metaprogramming element it's not going
to do something that is not described by
the generative models form is is that
like a a big goal of active influence
because I I mean it feels like you
without that it would just be nearly
impossible to to emulate you know the
same fires that you living organisms
would have because you we organisms
would have a lot of fire like almost you
know from our perspective almost
infinite amount of
f yes and depending on
the
nich it's um but definitely some people
that's similar
to what they might be interested in like
developing generalization capacities
through
metacognitive um nesting or through
observers with higher
complexity that might be something kind
of related to how Wolfram is approaching
it like with the Observer Theory and all
of that and like computational
capacity
David yeah just an observation uh can
you go back to the uh the branch map
that you had with um basian and fren was
[Music]
uh was related to what Susan was asking
it had a Bas theem at the bottom and it
had um active inference at the top I
believe was a tree tree map
figure one with the high and low road
yes okay yes all right yes so sorry so
yeah Fe so I guess just like visually I
construct it this way where could you
consider this if you linked base with
free energy principle that that would
you know cover a surface so in that case
if you could do that would you have Baye
over free energy or would it be free
energy over Baye or would it be
commutative if uh you can see the
structure
there maybe write it down like write it
out as a question for the chapter and
let's return to it but okay it sounds
interesting yeah it's outside of the
bounds of what we're covering so thanks
it's just hard to process in real time
but it sounds interesting okay
yeah anyone else like to we can go
totally any
Direction
with two or look ahead or look to some
other
part one more thought on the um question
about where like the priors come from
this is coming up later in chapter nine
but chapter nine is about integrating
real data so that kind of addresses some
of the questions that come up about how
to integrate with real systems because
like it seems like pretty clearly one
kind of thing to just write out a model
or like sketch it out and just propose
it and then it's another thing to
connect it to data and and use it in
like empirical settings so here's kind
of that model that is constructed of
like the rat and the
Tas and then but that's a map of the
rat's cognitive territory not claiming
to be a total description of the rat's
physiology just the team's decision as
analyzed a certain way um so it's the
Observer or the experimenter who's
passing what become observations to the
rat but they're actions from the
scientist and then the emitted actions
of the Rat are observations for the
scientist so it is it is possible to
understand like our role around like
building the generative model in terms
of this kind of laboratory
setting kind of consistent with the
origins and the behavioral analysis and
SPM like in a laboratory making a
cognitive map then that map is a map of
the
environments
and then that that was kind of explored
in that in a
really clear and interesting Way by by
this paper with ramstead Sak divid devel
and friston I'll put in the live
chat but they they they make very strong
claims like about that kind of
relationship essentially saying if this
is how you see the situation
then Fe is the best descriptor of
it so people
could descent from their conclusions or
from their um setup of the problem or or
other
features but it's a very strong claim
within this
setting and then the the fallacy fallacy
like the map territory fallacy is very
ly discussed like the map of San
Francisco is not the actual land or the
territory of San Francisco and there's
like the Bor his story about the Ono one
map and how that becomes not useful
because it's kind of like wrapped over
the real world so maps are always kind
of motivated by the right um course
gradings and then um so that's the map
territory fallacy
is falsely or inappropriately
articulating the map territory
relationship but then they are resp
responding to what they perceived is a
criticism of O Fe which is um once it's
acknowledged as a cognitive modeling
technique then people say well then it
is just a map we want the real territory
description and we want the real
thing so then that's like the fallacy
fallacy is their kind of term for the
overshoot it's like okay well then it
doesn't describe anything because you
can just construct whatever map you want
it's like yes you can construct whatever
map you want of San
Francisco and then what so that's kind
of interesting angle that they brought
out even a few years ago
David yeah so in terms of that I'm just
trying to think of how to how to
rephrase it um terms of the mapping
itself I mean obviously like through
periodic time change and everything but
if you created the map itself like if
you I'm thinking in terms of like wave
function collapse right if you're if
you're observing something directly it
will collapse the way it function just
you know as a basic overview of it but
if it's oblique to your perspective but
it's still within your it's not necessar
necessarily in your priors or it might
have be been dissolved from your prior
into something else that's kind of your
own inferential map which you're not
collab but you're utilizing without
having to you know use that extra energy
or any extra energy Beyond you know just
that distilled information that you have
that's kind of how I reinterpreted
that that sounds very interesting like
there's like a primary sensory mapping
that's like dealing with a collapse over
like primary observations or something
but then right so instead of like a
singular Viewpoint of the map and all of
its other points the Viewpoint comes
from you know a different perspective
that you're not particularly aware of at
the time of your
inferential connection to the map
itself so the map still exists but
you're not using any energy to look at
it
directly so it kind of mercades itself
over your own
perspective okay cool add more but it
sounds interesting Cheryl
okay yes hi um I've been um as you know
I'm new to this but I am very much
interested in the way cognition is
defined so I'm my first question is does
the AC of inference then just focus on
observable
behaviors because so much of what the
brain does is
implicit and is not going to actually
show up as a something that an outsider
could even
observe so I'll stop with that question
before I go
on it's a great question so I I wouldn't
say it models um only observable
behaviors but rather it is made clear
what is observable and what is not so
you can make a model that's fully
observable like a chessboard
where there is no difference between the
observations in the hidden State like of
the piece on the board so it's like a
fully observable system or you can have
a system where the only observation is
um a binary State and then there's like
very complex internal Dynamics and
another angle on that um is from this
paper with bongard L so here they talk
about this like poly Computing which is
that the
Observer is doing inference on what kind
of computation a material is doing so if
like there was an encrypted
communication to an observer who didn't
know it would look like
noise that's why the
observer's um situatedness is so
important because we we shouldn't just
assume just because it was noise to one
Observer doesn't mean that there isn't
something in that information stream but
it was their relationship of it that it
was perceived to be doing just noise
generation whereas in a different
reference frame that could have other
information that can't be ruled out even
from from any kind of noise pattern so
like I would say it's it's a big
philosophical and empirical question how
you model like the priors and the the
hyper priors and all this of
observers and that just like empirically
there are techniques that basian
researchers use to address some of these
things like testing the the influence of
different prior distributions or
building the initial priors from
empirical
data but certainly there's a lot of
expressivity and probably a lot of
complexity to to what you're asking
about right okay that that's helpful so
um active inference does not claim to be
the way that this works but a
way
yes that's totally true it's totally
true that's why it's often helpful to um
differentiate between like when are we
talking about like active inference as
is versus with how it can be which is
improving and learning active inference
or active inference versus an
alternative account of the same
phenomena something that like Ryan Smith
and other researchers do do and and
hopefully will happen more that's one
kind of comparative mode
which is a totally valid and important
mode because it's important um for
certain questions and situations and
everything like to know like does
reinforcement learning fit better than
active inference in this
setting there other times there's kind
of epistemic value even with just
developing along just an active model
but is always useful to have even really
radically different models like is this
predictor even better than just a coin
flip and then that helps calibrate it to
to like more reference points than just
parameter sweeps within the otim
model which then doesn't allow you to
make points about that in relationship
something that wasn't actually
explored um so I just have a question
about where to put
questions um because you're right I
think I need to write this out to get a
better idea of what it is that I'm even
asking you um but it has something to do
with the difference between implicit and
explicit so uh where would I where would
I kind of think this through on right
you could add a new row and like add it
to this table or you could like
literally just add it anywhere and okay
and then do at like active inference
Institute and then it it's just can be
added anywhere you type it or call yeah
okay great all right thank you but yeah
these are interesting questions like
does the implicit and explicit map on to
observations and hidden States
correct yeah and then is there another
implicit and explicit for modeling is
that the same one described by the
internal by the hidden States and by the
um observations not
necessarily right because at one point
I'm going to ask you about neur uh
neurons and neural development and the
the way that the brain
actually um in in in embryos grows
together mation how the these things it
doesn't seem like a basian thing um and
uh because they don't all come out
different in and you know in a in a
normal curve you you know most human
beings have their brains developed along
the same lines and so um I I just would
like to know
how active
inference what what part does it play as
you go down levels of analyses or way up
in levels of analyses
past just um
agents all all great questions on the
development line like the canalization
of development like the regularity
across individuals that's definitely a
big topic like Mike Levin and other
researchers especially have looked at
that like Wasington epigenetic landscape
and understanding how like cells come to
have morphology and then I mean you
brought up other things as well but yeah
those are
like those are all great great questions
all right thank you so
much any anyone else just go for
it yes go for
it um I thought we have a section for
cohort six questions
[Music]
um yeah and yeah when I was waiting for
the textbook I I do like to put down you
know my thoughts in there as well oh
awesome yeah let's look at let's look at
some right
now they do all go to the same
underlying thing but if you wanted to be
tagged with cohort 6 thank you for
suggesting yeah put it in
here and I'll make a chapter 3
one
okay
yes what happens if you just update the
prior with the posterior instead of
using K
Divergence um do you mean like what
happens if you update your belief just
like to last observation super simply
instead of calculating anything more
complex than that yeah without using the
supplies and you know I guess this to me
kind of feels like like a learning rate
kind of thing um is it is it like that
yeah like um it's also related to Colman
filter and smoothing so it's like if
we're um getting noisy thermometer
measurements I mean we could just update
our belief just to the noisiness of the
thermometer measurement and just treat
it like perfect measurement of a
underlying process but the Dynamics of
the underlying process like we might be
able to get a way better model by just
saying well it's a sinusoid hidden State
and then we're just sampling from it so
yeah I I guess it makes sense from that
perspective but from the perspective of
you know whether it's a fog or an apple
if you see an apple jump it kind of
feels like
oh like it's um
much it could be a much stronger update
that oh it is not an apple it's actually
a fog
now yeah like in this world there's a 1%
chance that apples jump so you're
totally right that if this was a apples
never jump like a heris encoded as um a
column in this Matrix yeah then it would
go 100% so it's
like in practice you can do things like
that that truncate or just like start
with no noise on a certain thing
y um Zach data yeah great question it's
um one that also came up actually
earlier so look at the cohort 5 um video
on like reinforcement learning but the
key difference is that in active
inference we're directly talking about
the joint distribution and the
likelihood of the generative
model and preferences so pragmatic value
the way that they come into with the
picture in decision making is by
checking the difference between the
preferences and the observations coming
in whereas in reinforcement learning
there's a secondary reward distribution
that's proposed on top of the
observation so like 37 degrees body
temperature is rewarding and then you
pursue rewarding
policies versus in active inference 37
is expected and preferred C and then
likely policies are
sampled that doesn't mean any given
active model is as good or better or
anything at all at all so it's totally
situational which one is more useful
which one you're more comfortable with
and so
on but that's the
difference I heard someone Susan said I
heard someone say active is based on
causality not correlation
well you can use it to study
correlations amongst variables you could
also use it like a basian causal draft
to study so-called causation amongst
variables
so then you could engage in the whole is
the causative map the territory's
causation that's a whole area like Mel
Andrews and others have explored some of
that
philosophy um and Judea Pearl kind of
and and other people delman in the
statistical causal
modeling with um Dynamic causal modeling
like if there's a causal relationship
identified in the hidden State between
two brain regions in the fmri study does
that mean they have a causal
relationship like those
are questions that there's a lot of
discussion
on
David yeah along those lines how would
that relate to like a co- causal
State co- causal State um could be
like here there's two distributions
here's temperature and humidity and they
both and then the output is the D point
so two things that jointly cause a third
thing right I'm also thinking in terms
of like a third that causes still a
singular in terms of like a zor if you
were thinking in terms of like a gated
where it's not a choice but rather it's
you know you have two
individuals making separate decisions
one person is the patient in the you
know the case we're talking about here
right terms of the patient being doing
EEG scan or something with the doctors
priors you know at you know going down
to that
0.01 right that 1% Apple frog you know
at what point is it co- causal then does
it become a zor or does it become still
in or state
or joint
co-state very interesting I think look
at this guest stream 67 if you haven't
which talks about like noisy independent
experts and about how like with sensor
arrays that having more noisy
uncorrelated which is to say noisy
components whereas like if all the
experts agreed on a test you'd actually
have low Precision relative to one with
an uncorrelated error
profile okay perfect I'll check that out
thank you
yeah someone else had their hand
raised um okay just to clarify we want
variation variational free energy to be
as small as possible approaching zero or
negative Infinity um in practice
approaching some number value that's in
arbit units um there was like a
discussion on the Discord General about
this that people could look at but like
the free energy values itself is going
to converge to
some situation specific minimal value
just like if you were doing least
squares like sum of squares minimization
for linear regression the best fit
regression would converge to like sum
sum of squares so just a a number sum
across the squared error differences
from the linear regression but then that
like value is depending on the number of
data points and the units and all this
other like random stuff not really
random stuff but it does depend on those
things so um that's why Delta free
energy and the gradient of free energy
is used and all of the physics grounding
is actually about the gradient around
the free energy and that's why it's like
incrementally optimizable because
there's a surface that gradients on free
energy can be taken on so it's like a
landscape like a free energy landscape
there's an elevation at that point
that's like the actual
score of like q and given Y and then
there's the local slopes that are used
for
optimization and then the simplest
optimization here is like is just go in
the direction that it's going to be
lower but that doesn't really matter
what the absolute value is
and then when it's when the change in
free energy is zero the model is like
converged to a stable
Point could be local could be Global
that's the whole challenge with like
model yeah this is a great question I
think maybe some people have put
things people outside of active
inference have written about like
so-called conspiracy theories and Basi
and belief updating um also definitely
some of these topics people have looked
at like people can add links but let's
continue all the other
questions um generating priers I mean in
practice they're specified by the person
who's making the generative
model
there should be many priors and policies
yeah to make the quote Whole
iguana so this is in chapter 10 but
chapter 10 is a lot like chapter
one so um this is like in contrast to
the research program of like let's study
which which is also a very useful
research program but kind of two two
paths diverging one of them is like
studying really narrow components like
let's study mechanotransduction in this
brain region of groph fruit
fly and then understand very narrow
features very
deeply um but scattered across like the
animal and and non-animal species and
then in contrast like this um
alternative holistic approach is model
the whole
uana which is like how about not just
super good on the homeostasis of
temperature on the Iguana then we know
nothing about this other component but
like think totally about
it so yeah it is very challenging to
make multimodal models because it's easy
to make a single like an ant colony
model with just foraging is easy but
then if it's like foraging and Nest
construction it's hard to do that
David yeah so in terms of that wouldn't
it wouldn't that come back then to
context free grammars and being able
to um compute better in that context
because at what point you know when you
start using frog iguana Apple I mean
isn't that giving context to the
measurement itself to begin
with yeah very interesting question I
think in the pedagogical context you
could replace it with like any other it
could be the the whole onion so like in
that sense it doesn't like it's not a
one specific just to be like clear um
but like yes the reason why that makes
sense or how somebody would know what to
do is reflective of
their ref I guess I guess it's kind of
how I'm seeing it is in terms of like if
you remove all the context from
everything you're if you have the
statistics remaining you could apply it
to you know your own inference in terms
of you know seeing that statistical
Dynamic amongst two other things that or
name something else you know that have
the same exact n values that might end
up you know then being if you remove the
context from it you know the statistical
correlation still
exists yeah there's there's a ton of
things to say about that I mean there
are priors I suppose that you're
bringing into that as
well cool let's explore it more but yes
it sounds interesting all right thanks
Thomas for the live streams on the noisy
experts that
was 67.1 I think 67.1
ntqr
Susan asks is degrees of freedom
computed in act INF and not
reinforcement that is not the case
degrees of freedom are in place anytime
statistics is being used so even if you
were to use linear regression or
reinforcement learning or neural network
or llm
Transformer any of those statistical
settings degrees of freedom are in
play Anova test every single statistic
setting with the meaning of what they
describe the degrees of freedom
of
not sure if I'm using the right term are
these equations proven either
mathematically or empirically or are
they useful
approximations it's a complex question
like in one sense all of the consistent
spaces in math sub subspaces and so on
like by virtue of the equal sign they're
all describing
topologies all of them could be reduced
to like 1 equals 1 which could come back
to like the axioms of how we are going
to be defining like numbers and equality
so there's an intrinsic logic to the
equations that describes like the fact
that it really is possible as um for
example uh yakup and some other people
have done like with equation 2.5 you
really can
go and look how the
different decompositions really of free
energy and expected free energy really
are related to each other
formally so there's an internal
consistency similar to the status of all
other like mathematical statistics or
like mathematical
physics does that provide an empirical
validity is a totally interesting
question it certainly does not provide
situational validity or
adequacy but then it's like a different
interesting question does it like what
are we looking for we say empirically
and like the live stream from just a few
days ago with Ryan
Smith um on the empirical
status is super relevant as I'm sure the
insights that is going to be like later
in the week with Ryan
Smith so like and he talked a little bit
about like his philosophy background in
this stream it was really
cool because most of his work is very
clinical and like has to do with with SC
like scientifically clinical empirical
okay any last
question so this was um chapter 2 low
road the what
slow chapter 3 kind of refreshes and
picks up on the high road with uh more
about the like transcendental
imperatives side that are not
necessarily Arch architecture
dependent so I think like in that um the
robotics work of JF clader at The
Institute he's used symbolic programming
to develop kind of an alternative low
road that's not distributional belief
based but it has the same high road
imperatives so just kind of an example
of how there can be like the same
why um same Tios same um ends could be
done with different low roads kind of
interesting topics that like come out
through chapter
three then having approached actim from
the two
sides chapter 4 goes into the formal
details of the generative model that's
the central artifact that's like what is
constructed and then chapter 5 gives a
bunch of studies and reviews on one of
the systems that's been the most studied
which is like the mamalian nervous
system so kind of just showing here's
what constructing system specific models
and linking them up looks
like and and here's what it looks like
in the several decades of study that
people have done in the mammal nervous
system just as kind of like a review SL
jumping off
point
any last SL comments or
thoughts
H um I watched a video
um with do uh Dr Jeff Beck um and I'm
not sure if I'm remembering this prop
but they were saying there's some people
trying to implement the Transformer
architecture within active
influence like does that make sense at
all or maybe I'm just remembering wrong
there's projects that are doing
everything from like active rappers
around Transformers to Transformer
rappers around llms to Transformers or
neural networks replacing specific
matrices in generative models like using
a neural network for a instead of just a
matrix with the dimensions of
observations by hidden States so there's
many possible combinations I don't know
what backck discussion it was but um he
did talk with Darius and they like
talked about markall blanket and brought
up like a lot of useful questions and
ments on this does that address it cool
cool yep right thank
you
bye